Finding Aid for Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering (University of Michigan) records, 1853-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering (University of Michigan) records 1853-2001 1960-1998
University of Michigan. Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering.
87138 Bimu C146 2
The Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering is a unit within the College of Engineering at the University of Michigan. The records span from 1853 to 2001 with the bulk of the material being from 1960-1998. The records cover a variety of topics, including documentation from the Alumni Association, Chi Epsilon chapter, faculty meeting minutes, and annual reports from the administration.
5.7 linear feet 7 boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by the Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering (Donor No. 1884, 5375 ) in 2003 and 2007 with additions made in February 2008 and May 2009.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and t enure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The of Civil and Environmental Engineering record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 3 and 7
Executive Officer Records -- Box 3
In 1853, Alexander Winchell was the first appointed Professor of Physics and Civil Engineering at the University of Michigan under the Department of Literature, Science and Art. In 1855, Professor William Peck became the second appointed as Professor of Civil Engineering. In the field of civil engineering, the first class, consisting of two men, graduated in 1860. In 1895, the College of Engineering was established as a separate entity from the College of Literature, Science, and Arts.
Within the College of Engineering was established the Department of Civil Engineering and Gardner Williams was appointed Professor of Civil Engineering. In 1904, the West Engineering Building was opened and the Department of Civil Engineering moved most of its operations to this site. In 1912, Henry Riggs was appointed the head of the Department of Civil Engineering. Riggs set up five specific divisions within the Department of Civil Engineering. They were Civil Engineering, Geodesy and Surveying, Hydraulic Engineering, Municipal and Sanitary Engineering, and Structural Engineering. In 1921, the Division of Geodesy and Surveying became its own department, and in 1922 the Division of Transportation Engineering was established. Lewis Gram became head of the department in 1928. In 1936, the Division of Hygiene and Public Health was established in the department. However, this division was later absorbed into the School of Public Health in 1941. At the same time, the Department of Geodesy and Surveying returned to the Department of Civil Engineering. Earnest Boyce became the head of the department in 1947. By 1949, the department had 369 undergraduate students enrolled, and 114 graduate students. During this year, the Michigan chapter of Chi Epsilon, the Civil Engineering Honors Society, was established.
In 1962, Frank Richart was appointed head of the department. The department was forced to revise its curricula in 1967 when the College of Engineering lowered the amount of credit hours required for undergraduates. In 1976, Robert Hanson was appointed head of the department. 1978 saw the discontinuation of both the Transportation Institute and the Division of Geodesy and Surveying within the department.
In recent years, the department expanded its name to the Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering and began offering a new undergraduate degree in environmental engineering. In 2013, the U.S. World and News Report ranked both the undergraduate and graduate programs in environmental engineering as 4th in their respective categories, and the programs in civil engineering ranked 8th and 7th respectively.
The records of the Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering records span from 1853 to 2001 with the bulk of the material being from 1960-1998. The records cover a variety of topics, including documentation from the Alumni Association, Chi Epsilon chapter, faculty meeting minutes, and annual reports from the administration. The records are organized in eight series: Administrative, Alumni Association, Chi Epsilon, Events, Faculty, Financial, Topical, and Photographs.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. Department of Civil Engineering.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. Department of Civil Engineering.; University of Michigan. Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering.; University of Michigan--Students.; Cissel, James H. (James Harlan), 1889-; Civil Engineering.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Administrative
  The Administrative series (2.65 linear feet, 1908-1998) is primarily made of annual reports covering 1908-1973 and 1983-1987. It also contains various department committee records and other documentation that was produced at the administrative level of the department, including departmental reviews in 1969 and 1981 as well as visiting committee reviews. Correspondence sent by the department and Gordon Van Wylen, former dean of the college, is contained in this series, as well.
  - Annual Report 1908-1973, 1983-1987, 19 folders (Box 1)
  - BSE Degree in Land Survey (Box 5)
  - Chair Advisory Committee 1991-1995, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Civil Engineering Department Name Change, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
  - College Honors and Awards, 1987-1992 (Box 5)
  - College Planning Retreat, December 1987 (Box 5)
  - Cost Sharing (Box 5)
  - Department Name Change, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
  - Department Review 1969, 1981, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Department Visiting Committee 1968, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Elimination of MSE in Public Works Administration (Box 5)
  - Equipment Requests from $55M Program (Box 5)
  - Equipment-Space-Rehabilitation, 1964-1968 (Box 5)
  - Exchange Agreements with Foreign Institutions (Box 5)
  - Expendable Research Fund #360078 (Box 5)
  - Graduate Recruitment 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Highway Safety Research Institute (Box 5)
  - Indonesian Visitors 1996 (Box 1)
  - Information for Alan Smith Report, August 1968 (Box 5)
  - Intellectual Inventory, 1973-1974, 1985-1986 (Box 5)
  - Jackson Extension Program 1979 (Box 1)
  - Keys (Box 6)
  - Michigan Department of State Highways, 1970-1972 (Box 6)
  - National Advisory Committee 1989 (Box 1)
  - Planning Committee (Box 1)
  - Public Relations Department 1998 (Box 1)
  - Reports of Department Chairs, 1999-2000, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Reshaping Graduate Education report, 1999 (Box 6)
  - Sea Grant, 1970-1975 (Box 6)
  - Undergraduate Advertising 1986-1988 (Box 1)
  - Visiting Professor Program 1989-1991 (Box 1)
- Alumni Association
  The Alumni Association series (0.3 linear feet, 1978-1986) is made up of various documents created by the alumni group as well as the Friends of Civil Engineering group. Material details activities and networking. The Friends Association's main purpose is to promote relations between alumni and other students and engineers. As such, the dealings of the Alumni Association often overlapped with the Friends Association.
  - Activities 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1978-1985 (Box 2)
  - Friends of Civil Engineering 1979 (Box 2)
  - General, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Meeting Record 1983 (Box 2)
  - Networking Report 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - Program Updates 1982 (Box 2)
  - Publications 1986 (Box 2)
- Chi Epsilon
  The Chi Epsilon series (0.4 linear feet, 1948-1989) contains documentation on the Michigan chapter of Chi Epsilon, the Civil Engineering Honors Society. Contained are booklets on the proceedings of the chapter, as well as lists of members, events and newsletters.
  - Faculty Advisor's Handbook (Box 2)
  - General 1954-1969 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter 1950-1971 (Box 2)
  - Petition to begin chapter 1948 (Box 2)
  - Policy and Procedures 1969 (Box 2)
  - Potential Members 1969-1982 (Box 2)
  - Ritual Guide 1959, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Schedules and Events 1964-1978, 1987-1989 (Box 2)
- Events
  The Events series (0.3 linear feet, 1973-2000) contains information on events put on by the department such as women's luncheon for faculty wives, picnics and Christmas gatherings as information on the events for Martin Luther King, Jr. Day and information on Tech Day, an event where the College of Engineering invites prospective students to explore the college.
  - Annual Christmas Gathering 1973-2001 (Box 2)
  - Department Picnic 1976-1990 (Box 2)
  - Martin Luther King, Jr. Day 1989-1994, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Social Event Calendar 1975-1983 (Box 2)
  - Tech Day 1988-1994 (Box 2)
  - Women's Luncheon for Faculty Wives 1976-2000 (Box 2)
- Faculty
  The Faculty series (0.6 linear feet, 1937, 1963-2001) is primarily made of faculty meeting minutes. Also included are biographies of various faculty members prepared in 1937 as part of the Encyclopedic Survey project and profiles from the 1980s, as well as a photographic roster of faculty members from 1974. Faculty rules and minutes of the College of Engineering faculty are included in this series.
  [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2028 ]
  - Biographies, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence (Box 7)
    - Bottum, Curt (Box 7)
    - Department Correspondence, 1987-1992, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Van Wylen, Dean Gordon, Correspondence (Box 7)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2028 ]
  - Environmental Committee (Box 7)
  - Executive Committee, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1985, 1989-1996, 1998, 2000-2001, 9 folders (Box 3)
  - Kanpur Indo-American File, 1969-1971 (Box 7)
  - Planning Committee (Box 7)
  - Staff Meetings (Box 7)
  - Rules of the Faculty Minutes, 1963-1984, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - New Faculty Recruitment (Box 3)
  - Prospects -- Goebel Chair of Advanced Technology, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - Search for Department Chair, 1984, 1999, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Financial
  The Financial series (0.2 linear feet, 1941-1951, 1987-1988) contains data from the academic budget, 1941-1951, and information of fellowship awards available in 1987-1988.
  - Academic Budget, 1941-1947, 1949-1951, 2 folders (Box 3)
    [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2028 ]
  - Fellowship Awards, 1987-1988 (Box 3)
  - Purchase Order, 1977 (Box 3)
- Topical
  The Topical series (0.4 linear feet, 19853-1997) contains various files that do not fit the scope of the other series. Included are files such as correspondence, excerpts from university catalogues on civil engineering classes offered at the University from 1853-1860, documents on the Society of Women Engineers, and information on the department's earthquake assistance in Egypt.
  - Center for Robotics and Integrated Manufacturing (Box 5)
  - Computer Network Proposals, 1994-1997 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1993-1994, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Diversity Issues, 1997 (Box 5)
  - Egypt Earthquake Assistance, 1992-1993 (Box 5)
  - Engineering Aspects of Peru Earthquake, 1970 (Box 5)
  - Engineers Council for Professional Development (Box 5)
  - MTC Update Publication, 1987-1988 (Box 5)
  - Potholes, #384547 (Box 5)
  - Regent Meeting Excerpts on Civil Engineering, 1912-1929 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook, outsized (Box 5)
  - Society of Women Engineers, 1990-1992 (Box 5)
  - University Catalogue excerpts of Civil Engineering Classes, 1853-1860 (Box 5)
  - University Committee on Water Resources, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Walter Weber Award, 1977-1978 (Box 5)
  - Weber, Walter articles (Box 5)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (0.2 linear feet and one scrapbook, 1905, 1949, 1980s-2001) includes an original 1905 group photograph of the 1905 Civil Engineering students, a 1949 portrait of structural engineering professor James Cissel, and photographs of faculty, staff, students and facilities from the 1980s and 1990s. A scrapbook covering 1985-2001 shows various events, groups, faculty and students.
  - Civil Engineers Class of 1905, 1905 (Box 4)
  - James Cissel portrait 1949 (Box 4)
  - Photographs, labeled (Box 4)
  - Photographs, unlabeled (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook 1985-2001 (Box 4)
  - College Bulletin photographs (Box 5)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 5)
  - Photographic Roster of the Engineering Faculty, 1960, 1966-1967, 3 volumes (Box 5)
  - Photographic Roster of the Engineering Faculty, 1974-1975 (Box 5)